<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The evil spirit cast-out. Being a true relation of the manner of performing the famous operation or cure, on the maiden gentlewoman, whose body was possessed with an evil spirit. With the carriage and behaviour of the evil spirit ... the several ways and means that were used to drive or cast-out the devil ... the contest between the devil and the doctor ... the strange noise, horrid cry, and great blast of wind, which happened just at the spirits departure.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3555A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176802</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51784548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2706:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The evil spirit cast-out. Being a true relation of the manner of performing the famous operation or cure, on the maiden gentlewoman, whose body was possessed with an evil spirit. With the carriage and behaviour of the evil spirit ... the several ways and means that were used to drive or cast-out the devil ... the contest between the devil and the doctor ... the strange noise, horrid cry, and great blast of wind, which happened just at the spirits departure.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Golding,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed and entred according to order."</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustration on t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Glasgow Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Exorcism --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spirit possession --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174957:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:174957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <p>The Evil Spirit Caſt-out. Being a True RELATION Of the Manner of Performing the Famous Operation or Cure, ON THE Maiden Gentlewoman, <hi>Whoſe Body was Poſſeſſed with an</hi> Evil Spirit.</p>
            <p>WITH The Carriage and Behaviour of the EVIL SPIRIT, while the Cure was Performing: The ſeveral Ways and Means that were uſed to Drive or Caſt-out the Devil out of the Body Poſſeſſed. The Conteſt between the DEVIL and the DOCTOR before he quitted the Party. ALSO, The ſtrange Noiſe, Horrid Cry, and great Blaſt of Wind, which happened juſt at the Spirits Departure.</p>
            <p>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Golding.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_exorcism">
            <pb facs="tcp:174957:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:174957:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <head>The <hi>Evil Spirit Caſt-out:</hi> Being a True Relation of the manner of performing the Famous Operation or Cure on the Maiden Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONE Mrs. — a Maiden Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, having languiſhed for ſome time under very ſore and grievous Afflictions, which, by the ſtrange Geſtures and Actions of her Body, plainly declar'd her to have been either <hi>Bewitch'd</hi> or <hi>Poſſeſs'd</hi> with an <hi>Evil Spirit:</hi> Her Relations came to me, and inform'd me, That they had ſpent much upon ſeveral able Phyſicians, who pretended to Cure her, but could not, and deſir'd me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the Cure, which accordingly I did; upon Examination, I found that her Fits ſeiz'd her much about the ſame time every day, every of which laſted about the ſpace of Twelve hours; in which time ſhe ſhriek'd and cry'd out in a pitiful manner,
<pb facs="tcp:174957:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->
               <pb facs="tcp:174957:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->
               <pb facs="tcp:174957:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:174957:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->that, thro' the extremity of her Afflicton, ſhe was brought to ſuch a weak Condition, that ſhe was not able to ſtir or move any part of her Limbs or Body, from her Waſte to her Feet. The Maid was brought to my Houſe, and, by demanding and asking ſeveral Queſtions of her, I found that ſhe was <hi>Poſſeſſed by the Devil,</hi> for ſhe could not once name the Name of <hi>God, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. but ſhe would immediately fall into Fits, and be ſtrangely Tormented. I councelled her Father to go to ſome Pious Divine, to make an Eſſay in the matter, and to ſee what his Devotion could do, he anſwer'd me, That he had done it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, but to no purpoſe; for one Doctor — the Miniſter of the Pariſh, a Learned, Judicious, and Pious Man, had ſpent ſome time in attempting to do it, yet could not prevail, but was forced to deſiſt, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed their ſeeking Remedy of ſome body elſe, whom <hi>God</hi> might give Strength and Faith to perform ſo great a Work.</p>
            <p>This did ſomewhat diſcourage me, yet, for the ſake of my Reputation, I did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, and (by <hi>God</hi>'s Bleſſing) effect the Cure. Some there are who are Poſſeſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:174957:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->whom the <hi>Devil</hi> at ſome times leaveth, but he never left this Maid, from the time he firſt entered into her. Her Fits gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeized her about Nine a Clock at Night, and held her till Eight the next day; in the interim of which, ſhe was hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly Tormented, making divers Noiſes, as Howling, Crying, Shrieking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> twiſting and turning her Body up and down, rowling about the Room, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From the hour of Eight in the Forenoon, until Twelve, ſhe would give Reſolution to all manner of Demands, but chiefly if her Mother propounded them. She would tell of Things Loſt, who had them; how and where they ſhould be found, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſtrange Queſtions, which always proved true: I could inſtance ſeveral, but for brevity ſake, I paſs them over. I come now to the manner and method of my Curing her.</p>
            <p>The Chamber being made as cloſe as with convenience it could be, I took <hi>Frankinſence, Roſemary,</hi> and <hi>Myrrh,</hi> and made a Perfume in the Chamber, which I continued to do till I had finiſhed the Cure: I oftentimes gave the Maid the
<pb facs="tcp:174957:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->Diſtilled Waters of <hi>Roſemary, Angelica,</hi> and <hi>Marigolds.</hi> When I laid my hands upon the Maid, the <hi>Devil</hi> in her began to ſtrive againſt me very much, yet I held my hold; and having got her at an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, I held her faſt, and did very often repeat theſe words, <hi>In the name of Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>I Command thee to come forth;</hi> yet notwithſtanding the Spirit was very obſtinate. I gave the Maid of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Waters very often, and then Prayed again, and as often repeated the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid words, for I reſolved not to deſiſt till the <hi>Devil</hi> did leave her; and thus I continued for about Two hours. At length the <hi>Devil</hi> inviſibly left her, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a hideous Noiſe, with a horrible Cry, and raiſed a ſuddain violent Blaſt of Wind, but did me no harm at all: Soon after the <hi>Devil</hi> did come forth of the Maid, ſhe began to <hi>Speak;</hi> and, within a ſmall time often, by the Bleſſing of <hi>God,</hi> upon ſuch Remedies as I apply'd, ſhe remains per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well.</p>
            <p>I will relate one thing more, which was generally in the time of her Fits; <hi>Three</hi> Pins were brought to her, and yet
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174957:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->but one at a time, and when ſhe receiv'd them, ſhe ſeem'd to <hi>Rejoyce,</hi> would <hi>Laugh</hi> and <hi>Smile,</hi> and put the Pins into her Mouth, which her Friends took from her, leſt it ſhould Choak her, yet ſhe was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to part with them. They had a Box full of them, for ſhe had <hi>Three</hi> brought to her every Night for a long Seaſon, and that very Night which I caſt the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> out of her, ſomething brought her <hi>Two</hi> before my Face. It was obſerv'd, That while I was performing this <hi>Buſineſs</hi> that <hi>Three Women</hi> were ſeen by my <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> to walk about my <hi>Houſe,</hi> and near the Window, where I did this <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> which we judged were <hi>Three Witches,</hi> who the <hi>Father</hi> ſuſpected, and ſince <hi>Proſecuted Them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vid. <hi>An Exact Account at large of this Relation, in Doctor</hi> Blagrave'<hi>s</hi> Book, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> Aſtrological Cures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:174957:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Bleſſed Lord, the Father of Mercies, and the God of all Comforts, we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Thee, look down in pity and compaſſion upon this thy Afflicted Servant, Thou writeſt bitter things againſt her, and makes her poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs her former Iniquities, Thy Wrath lyeth hard upon her, and her Soul is full of Trouble, But, O Merciful God, who haſt Written thy Holy Word for our Learning, that we through Patience, and Comfort of thy Holy Spirit, may have hope; Give her a right underſtanding of her Self, and of thy Threats and Promiſes, that ſhe may neither cast away his Confidence in Thee, nor place it any where but in Thee; give her ſtrength againſt all her Temptations, and heal all her Diſtempers; Break not the Bruiſed Read, nor Quench the Smoaking Flax; Sbut not up Thy tender Mercies in Diſpleaſure, but make her to hear of Joy and Gladneſs, that the Bones which Thou haſt broken may Rejoyce; Deliver her from fear of the Enemy, and lift up the light of Thy Countenance upon her, and give her Peace, through the Merits and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174957:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
